A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Publications (Non-Grant Related), Accession 2017:050 FA1304
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Publications (Non-Grant Related), Accession 2017:050
1949-2016
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA1304
45.84 Cubic Feet 113 boxes - 97 letter document containers, 14 legal document containers, 1 Paige box, and 1 oversize document box (16.5x12.5)
Arrangement
Materials are arranged as received from the Ford Foundation in 2017. Boxes 110-113 contain duplicate copies of various publications. They are listed intellectually with the first recorded instance of the publication in the finding aid.
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation was chartered by Henry and Edsel Ford in 1936 "to receive and administer funds for scientific, educational and charitable purposes, all for the public welfare", and initially served the Ford family's charitable interests in the Detroit area. Following the deaths of Edsel Ford (1943) and Henry Ford (1947), the Foundation was propelled to the forefront of philanthropy as the largest American foundation in terms of both endowment and yearly expenditures, and with an international scope to its major program areas.
During the Foundation's first twenty years its major programs were in international economic development, primary and higher education, educational and public broadcasting, behavioral sciences, civil liberties, urban development, fine arts and the humanities. The Ford Foundation also partnered with the Rockefeller Foundation in supporting agricultural development in South America, Africa, and Southeast Asia. Since the 1970s, the Foundation has also pioneered programs in women's rights, energy policy, micro-financing in under-developed countries, establishing human rights groups, and improving international HIV/AIDS education.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This material was transferred to RAC in 2017 by the Ford Foundation and ingested by RAC as Accession 2017:050.
Related Materials
Ford Foundation records, Publications (FA767) http://dimes.rockarch.org/FA767/collection
Ford Foundation records, Special Collections Publications (FA1395) http://dimes.rockarch.org/FA1395/collection
Ford Foundation records, Publications (Non-Grant Related), Accessions 2017:079 and 2017:089 (FA1394) http://dimes.rockarch.org/FA1394/collection
Separated Materials
Special format items have been separated from the body of the collection and assigned a unique separation number, as noted. Requests to access open special formats should reference the unique separation number.
Scope and Contents
Ford Foundation records, Publications (Non-Grant Related), Accession 2017:050 consists of pamphlets, reprints, brochures, reports, conference papers, and other publications by the Ford Foundation or by authors involved in Ford Foundation projects.
The subject areas of these publications reflect the Ford Foundation's areas of interest, including philanthropy, higher education, public education, the arts and humanities, equal opportunity, women's programs, housing, urban and local programs, working-class concerns, communications and journalism, administration of justice, resources and the environment, the energy policy project, and international programs related to agriculture, education, international studies, and population.
The collection also houses working publication files, including publication design files, correspondence and memoranda, distribution files, and press materials. These files can be identified by a title that will include "Job" and a series of numbers followed by the name of the publication.
Ford Foundation; Agriculture; Arts; Community development; Education, Higher; Education -- Public services; Energy policy -- Environmental aspects; Housing; Humanities; International development; International education; Journalism; Philanthropy; Population; Urban development; Women's programs
- Ford Foundation Publications, 1
  - Report on the Study for The Ford Foundation on Policy and Program (2 copies), 1949 November (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Future of The International Economic Order: An Agenda for Research, C. Fred Bergsten (2 copies), 1973 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Growing Up Forgotten: A Review of Research and Programs Concerning Early Adolescence, A Report to the Ford Foundation, Joan Lipitz (2 copies), 1977 (Box 1, Folder 3, Box 110, Folder 1288)
  - Resúmenes Analíticos en Educación, Horacio Walker, 1990 December (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Industrialism and Industrial Man in Retrospect: A Critical Review of the Ford Foundation's Support for the Inter-University Study of Labor, James L. Cochrane (2 copies), 1979 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Getting Men Involved: Strategies for Early Childhood Programs, James A. Levine, Dennis T. Murphy, PhD, and Sherrill Wilson, PhD, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Social Science Research on Population and Development: Papers Presented at a Conference at the Ford Foundation, New York City (2 copies), 1974 October 29-30 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Dealing with Drug Abuse: A Report to the Ford Foundation, The Drug Abuse Survey Project, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Poverty and Malnutrition in Latin America: Early Childhood Intervention Programs, A Report to the Ford Foundation, Ernesto Pollitt (2 copies), 1980 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - La Enseñanza de Dirección de Empresas en España, Management Education in Spain, William C. Frederick and Chadwick J. Haberstroth (2 copies), 1969 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Investment in Innovation: An Historical Appraisal of the Fund for the Advancement of Education, Paul Woodring (2 copies), 1970 (Box 3, Folder 11, Box 4, Folder 11a)
  - The Political Economy of Education: A Bibliography of Ford Foundation Supported Publications, 1968-1980 (2 copies), 1981 April (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - International Studies in Six European Countries: United Kingdom, France, Federal Republic of Germany, The Netherlands, Sweden, Italy, Reports to the Ford Foundation (2 copies), 1976 June (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Energy Research and Development: Papers Prepared for the Energy Policy Project of the Ford Foundation, J. Herbert Hollomon and Michel Grenon, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Potential Fuel Effectiveness in Industry: A Report to the Energy Policy Project of the Ford Foundation, Elias P. Gyftopoulos, Lazaros J. Lazaridis, Thomas F. Widmer, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Crisis in the Workplace: Occupational Disease and Injury, Nicolas A. Ashford (2 copies), 1976 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Understanding China: An Assessment of American Scholarly Resources, John M. H. Lindbeck (2 copies), 1971 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    Scope and Contents
    1 paperback, 1 hardcover
  - Exploring Energy Choices: A Preliminary Report, Energy Policy Project of the Ford Foundation (2 copies), 1974 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - State Environmental Management: Case Studies of Nine States, Elizabeth H. Haskell and Victoria S. Price (2 copies), 1973 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Research Universities and the National Interest: A Report from Fifteen University Presidents (2 copies), 1977 December (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Humanistic Education: An Interpretation, Elizabeth Leonie Simpson, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    A Report to the Ford Foundation
  - A Debate on A Time to Choose, A Critique, William Tavoulareas; A Reply, Carl Kaysen (2 copies), 1977 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    Hardcovers
  - Financing the Energy Industry: A Report to the Energy Policy Project of the Ford Foundation, Jerome E. Hass, Edward J. Mitchell, Bernell K. Stone (2 copies), 1974 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Energy Policy: Industry Perspectives: A Report to the Energy Policy Project of the Ford Foundation, John E. Gray, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - The Value of College: a Non-Economist's View, Harold Howe II (2 copies), 1975 November 10 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Public interest Law: Five Years Later, Ford Foundation, American Bar Association (2 copies), 1976 March (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - Ford Foundation Activities In Non-Commercial Broadcasting 1951-1976 (2 copies), undated (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - L'Assistance Fournie par la Foundation Ford en Afrique du Nord, Ford Foundation Assistance in North Africa (2 copies), 1974 September (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - Racial Segregation: Two Policy Views, Reports to the Ford Foundation (2 copies), 1979 October (Box 7, Folder 29)
    Federal Agencies and Urban Segregation: Steps Toward Coordinated Action by Gary Orfield and Mounting a Concerted Federal Attack on Urban Segregation: A Preliminary Exploration by William L. Taylor
  - Population Issues: From Obscurity to Worldwide Interest (2 copies), 1974-1975 (Box 7, Folder 30)
    I. Population: Before and After Bucharest by Lyle Saunders II. Ford Foundation Programs: Review and Projection by Oscar Harkavy
  - Barriers: A New Look at the Needs of Young Adolescents (2 copies), 1979 (Box 7, Folder 31)
  - Litigation on Behalf of Women: A Review for the Ford Foundation, Margaret A. Berger (2 copies), 1980 May (Box 8, Folder 32)
  - Women's Studies in the US, Catharine R. Stimpson with Nina Kressner Cobb (2 copies), 1986 June (Box 8, Folder 33)
  - Venture Capital, A Ford Foundation Reprint from Black Enterprise, Anthony Mason and Robert Braswell (2 copies), 1972 (Box 8, Folder 34)
  - Ford Foundation Assistance in the Arab Middle East and North Africa, 1979 August (Box 8, Folder 35)
  - Poor, Rural, and Southern, A Ford Foundation Report (3 copies), 1978 December (Box 8, Folder 36, Box 110, Folder 1287)
    Orange cover version in Box 110
  - Minority Admissions and Performance in Graduate Study: A Preliminary Study of Fellowship Programs of the Ford Foundation and the Danforth Foundation, Rodney Hartnett and Benjamin F. Payton (2 copies), 1977 August 2 (Box 8, Folder 37)
    A Ford Foundation Report
  - Models for Reforming Education in the City, Edward J. Meade, Jr. (2 copies), 1973 May 14 (Box 8, Folder 38)
    A Ford Foundation Reprint: Adapted from remarks given by Mr. Meade before the Minneapolis Citizens Committee on Public Education
  - Working Against Hunger, Ford Foundation Grants in Agriculture (2 copies), 1978 February (Box 8, Folder 39)
  - A Debate on A Time to Choose, A Critique, William Tavoulareas; A Reply, Carl Kaysen (2 copies), 1977 (Box 8, Folder 40)
    Paperbacks
  - The Ford Foundation Neighborhood and Family Initiative: Building Collaboration: An Interim Report (2 copies), 1993 April (Box 8, Folder 41)
    A Chapin Hall Report, The Chapin Hall Center for Children at the University of Chicago
  - That 51 Per Cent: Ford Foundation Activities Related to Opportunities for Women (2 copies), 1974 April (Box 8, Folder 42)
  - Current Interests of the Ford Foundation, (2 copies in Chinese), 1976-1977 (Box 8, Folder 43)
  - Current Interests of the Ford Foundation (2 copies), 1974 March (Box 8, Folder 44)
  - Created Equal: A Report on Ford Foundation Women's Programs (2 copies), 1986 October (Box 8, Folder 45)
  - Perspectives on Partnerships (2 copies), undated (Box 9, Folder 46)
    Community Development Partnership Strategy; Corporate and community leaders speak out on a collaborative strategy to revitalize America's urban and rural communities
  - Student Aid and the Urban Poor by the Washington Office of the College Board (2 copies), 1981 January (Box 9, Folder 47)
    Ford Foundation Series on Higher Education in the Cities
  - Exploring Energy Choices: A Preliminary Report, Energy Policy Project of the Ford Foundation (2 copies), 1974 (Box 9, Folder 48)
    Contains press release from March 31, 1974
  - Ecology and Resource Development in Southeast Asia (2 copies), 1973 August (Box 9, Folder 49)
  - Serving the Earth: The Ford Foundation's Environmental Program, Its Evolution and Underlying Philosophy, McGeorge Bundy and Gordon Harrison (2 copies), undated (Box 9, Folder 50)
  - The International Economic Order: A Report to the Ford Foundation, C. Fred Bergsten and John E. Mathieson (2 copies), 1973 September (Box 9, Folder 51)
  - Directory of Ford Foundation Fellows in Reproductive Biology (2 copies), 1960-1972 (Box 9, Folder 52)
  - An Inquiry into the Uses of Instructional Technology, James W. Armsey and Norman C. Dahl (2 copies), 1973 (Box 9, Folder 53)
  - La Fundacion Ford en Mexico y Centro Mexico, The Ford Foundation in Mexico and Central America (2 copies), 1967 February (Box 9, Folder 54)
  - Ford Foundation in Malaysia and Singapore (3 copies), 1967 (Box 9, Folder 55)
  - Urbanization in Venezuela: An International Urbanization Survey Report to the Ford Foundation, John P. Robin and Frederick C. Terzo (2 copies), 1972 (Box 10, Folder 56)
  - Urbanization in Colombia: An International Urbanization Survey Report to the Ford Foundation, John P. Robin and Frederick C. Terzo (2 copies), 1972 (Box 10, Folder 57)
  - Urbanization in Peru: An International Urbanization Survey Report to the Ford Foundation, John P. Robin and Frederick C. Terzo, 1972 (Box 10, Folder 58)
  - Urbanization in Chile: An International Urbanization Survey Report to the Ford Foundation, John P. Robin and Frederick C. Terzo (2 copies), 1972 (Box 10, Folder 59)
  - Urbanization in Jamaica: An International Urbanization Survey Report to the Ford Foundation, James W. Trowbridge, 1972 (Box 10, Folder 60)
  - Urbanization in Zambia: An International Urbanization Survey Report to the Ford Foundation, Allan J. F. Simmance (2 copies), 1972 (Box 10, Folder 61)
  - The Ford Foundation Program in Argentina (2 copies), 1964 February (Box 10, Folder 62)
  - Urbanization in Nigeria: An International Urbanization Survey Report to the Ford Foundation, Leslie Green and Vincent Milone (2 copies), 1972 (Box 10, Folder 63)
    A Planning Commentary
  - Urbanization in Tropical Africa: An International Urbanization Survey Report to the Ford Foundation, Colin Rosser (2 copies), 1972 (Box 10, Folder 64)
    A Demographic Introduction
  - Four Minorities and the Ph.D.: Ford Foundation Graduate Fellowships for Blacks, Chicanos, Puerto Ricans, and American Indians (2 copies), 1973 October (Box 10, Folder 65)
  - Ford Foundation Directives and Terms of Reference for the 1960s, 1962 June (Box 10, Folder 66)
    Includes Policy Directives, Program Directives, Operational Directives, and Terms of Reference
  - Ford Foundation Directives for the 1960's Supporting Materials Volumes I & II, Program Evaluations, 1951-1962, Program Proposals for the 1960s, 1962 June (Box 11, Folder 67)
    Includes sections titled: Education, International Training and Research Program, Humanities, Arts, Science and Engineering, Behavioral Sciences, Public Affairs, Economic Development and Administration, International Affairs, and Overseas Development
  - Ford Foundation Directives for the 1960's Supporting Materials Volumes III & IV, Interviews and Submissions, Special Papers and Working Documents, 1962 June (Box 11, Folder 68)
    Parts I-V
  - Ford Foundation Board of Trustees Future Program Planning Project: 1. The Hungry, Crowded, Competitive world, 1976 (Box 11, Folder 69)
    Includes staff commentary and discussion papers from Schultz, Islam, Legesse, Geertz/Hirschman, Berelson, International Food Policy Research Institute
  - Ford Foundation Board of Trustees Future Program Planning Project: 2. Democratic Policy and How It Works, With Special Reference to the United States, 1976 (Box 11, Folder 70)
    Staff commentary and discussion papers from: Huntington, Silvert, Kothari, Calabresi, Shils, and Reid
  - Ford Foundation Board of Trustees Future Program Planning Project: 3. Values, Society, and Culture, 1976 (Box 11, Folder 71)
    Staff commentary and discussion papers from Cardoso, Tracy, Miller, Nozick, and Hamilton
  - Ford Foundation Board of Trustees Future Program Planning Project: 4. The Generation and Spread of Knowledge and Its Application to Change in Society, 1976 (Box 11, Folder 72)
    Staff commentary and discussion papers from: Haskins, Roche, Ben-David, and Kaplan
  - Ford Foundation Board of Trustees Future Program Planning Project: 5. Economic Growth and Distribution of Economic Opportunity and Benefits Among Men and Nations, 1976 (Box 11, Folder 73)
    Staff commentary and discussion papers from: Okun, Levitan, Haq, Johnson, Gordon, and Sowell
  - Ford Foundation Board of Trustees Future Program Planning Project: 6. Justice, Fairness, and Human Rights, 1976 (Box 11, Folder 74)
    Staff commentary and discussion papers from: Chalidze, Cariola, Edelman, Hastie, Tyler
  - Ford Foundation Board of Trustees Future Program Planning Project: 7. War, Peace, and Cooperation Among Nations, 1976 (Box 11, Folder 75)
    Staff commentary and discussion papers from: Bull, Nye, Brewer, and Rubenstein
  - Ford Foundation Board of Trustees Future Program Planning Project: 8. The Nature of the Individual and His Fulfillment, 1976 (Box 11, Folder 76)
    Staff commentary and discussion papers from: Keniston, Olds, March, Achebe, Huxtable, Kozol, and Olson
  - Faculty Collective Bargaining: Impact on Planning by Fred E. Crossland (2 copies), 1976 (Box 12, Folder 77)
    A Ford Foundation Reprint from Intellect, this article is based on remarks prepared for delivery on July 22, 1976, at the 11th Annual International Conference of the Society for College and University Planning, Washington, DC
  - Left-Handed Fastballers: Scouting and Training America's Grass-Roots Leaders, 1966-1977, David Nevin (3 copies), 1981 August (Box 12, Folder 78, Box 110, Folder 1284)
    A report based on a study for the Ford Foundation conducted by David Nevin
  - Race and the Third World City: An International Urbanization Survey Report to the Ford Foundation, Hugh Tinker (2 copies), 1972 (Box 12, Folder 79)
  - Looking Back, Moving Ahead: A Decade of School-Finance Reform by James A. Kelly (2 copies), 1980 (Box 12, Folder 80)
    Presented at the Ford Foundation Conference on the Politics of Equity: Education Finance, State-Local Taxes, and Children's Services, held in San Antonio, Texas, May 11-15, 1980
  - Los Hispanos: Problemas y Oportunidades (2 copies), 1984 June (Box 12, Folder 81)
    Resumen de la actual situacion demografica, economica, social y politca de los hispanos en los Estados Unidos y de las iniciativas tomadas por la Fundacion Ford para hacer frente a las necesiadades de esta polcacio eb aumento y determinar sus efectos sobre la sciedad estadounidense.
  - Reflections on a Multi-Racial Society, Franklin A. Thomas (2 copies), 1983 February (Box 12, Folder 82)
    An address delivered as part of the Granada Guildhall Lecture series in London on November 1, 1982
  - Too Little, Too Late: Services for Teenage Parents, Elizabeth McGee (2 copies), 1982 October (Box 12, Folder 83)
    A working paper from the Ford Foundation, an examination of some major programs now operating in the United States to serve teenage parents and their children, including a look at the range and quality of available service and candid comments by service providers.
  - The Search for a New Economic Order, A Ford Foundation Report (2 copies), 1982 February (Box 12, Folder 84)
  - A Quest for Better Contraception: The Ford Foundation's Contribution to Reproductive Science and Contraceptive Development 1959-1983, Roy Hertz, MD, PhD (2 copies), 1984 September (Box 12, Folder 85)
  - Women, Children, and Poverty in America, A Working Paper from the Ford Foundation (2 copies), 1985 January (Box 12, Folder 86)
    A look at the problems facing low-income families headed by women and some current and planned Ford Foundation responses
  - El Programa de la Fundación Ford en el Perú, Ford Foundation Program in Peru (2 copies), 1974 December (Box 12, Folder 87)
  - Current Interests of the Ford Foundation in 1978 and 1979 (2 copies), 1978-1979 (Box 12, Folder 88)
  - Ford Foundation International Programs (2 copies), 1979 July (Box 12, Folder 89)
  - Minding the Children: Ford Foundation Assistance to Child-Care Programs (2 copies), 1980 March (Box 12, Folder 90)
  - Minorities and Housing: Are the Doors Really Open?, A Ford Foundation Reprint, Robert Chandler (2 copies), 1979 August (Box 12, Folder 91)
  - Foundations and Public-Private Ventures, A Ford Foundation Reprint, Franklin A. Thomas (2 copies), 1979 (Box 12, Folder 92)
    Reprinted from the Ford Foundation's Annual Report for 1979
  - The Local Initiatives Support Corporation (LISC): A Private-Public Venture for Community and Neighborhood Revitalization (2 copies), 1980 May (Box 12, Folder 93)
    A Ford Foundation Background Paper
  - Nuclear Power Issues and Choices, 1977 (Box 12, Folder 94)
    Overview, Excerpt from the Report of the Nuclear Energy Policy Study Group, Sponsored by the Ford Foundation, Administered by The MITRE Corporation
  - Understanding Population, Ira Mothner (2 copies), 1976 September (Box 13, Folder 95)
  - Black & Hispanic Art Museums: A Vibrant Cultural Resource, Azade Ardali (2 copies), 1989 December (Box 13, Folder 96)
  - Ford Foundation Current Interests 1986 and 1987, 1986 June (Box 13, Folder 97)
  - Ford Foundation Assistance in Eastern and Southern Africa (2 copies), undated (Box 13, Folder 98)
  - Ford Foundation Indonesia (2 copies), 1979 January (Box 13, Folder 99)
  - That 51%... Plus*, Joyce Pandolfi (2 copies), 1979 February (Box 13, Folder 100)
    A Ford Foundation Report - In 1974, when the Ford Foundation first published a report on its activities related to opportunities for women titled That 51 Per Cent, the female proportion of the United States population was 51.05 per cent. At the writing of this new report, in 1978, the proportion had increased slightly, to 51.25 per cent, but the increase in strength of the women's movement was substantially greater.
  - L'Aide de la Fondation Ford a L'Afrique Occidentale et Centrale, Ford Foundation Assistance in West and Central Africa (2 copies), 1977 October (Box 13, Folder 101)
  - Widening the Mainstream of American Culture: A Ford Foundation Report on Ethnic Studies, Jack Bass (2 copies), 1978 October (Box 13, Folder 102)
  - Mediating Social Conflict, A Ford Foundation Report (2 copies), 1978 October (Box 13, Folder 103)
  - Go-Betweens for Social Change, Mitchell Sviridoff (2 copies), 1978 March (Box 13, Folder 104)
  - Ford Foundation Grants in Resources and Environment (2 copies), 1978 October (Box 13, Folder 105)
  - Improving Cognitive Ability in Chronically Deprived Children, Harrison McKay, Leonardo Sinisterra, Arlene McKay, Hernando Gomez, Pascuala Lloreda (2 copies), 1978 (Box 13, Folder 106)
  - The United Nations and the Iran-Iraq War, A Ford Foundation Conference Report, 1987 August (Box 13, Folder 107)
  - Corrective Capitalism: The Rise of America's Community Development Corporations, A Report to the Ford Foundation, Neal R. Pierce and Carol F. Steinbach (2 copies), 1987 July (Box 13, Folder 108)
  - Toward A More Perfect Union: Basic Skills, Poor Families, and our Economic Future, Gordon Berlin and Andrew Sum (2 copies), 1988 February (Box 13, Folder 109)
    Ford Foundation Project on Social Welfare and the American Future, Occasional Paper 3
  - The Ford Foundation and China (3 blue copies and 2 gray copies), 1991 January (Box 13, Folder 110)
  - Investing for Social Gain: Reflections on Two Decades of Program-Related Investments, A Ford Foundation Report (2 copies), 1991 December (Box 13, Folder 111)
  - Men and Women: At Home and in the Workplace, Current Debates and Future Directions, Charles Brumfield, Arlie Hochschild, Rhona Rapoport, Beth Salerno, Faith Wohl (2 copies), 1991 May (Box 14, Folder 111A, Box 111, Folder 1299)
    Ford Foundation's Women's Program Forum
  - Financing an Effective United Nations: A Report of the Independent Advisory Group on UN Financing (2 copies), 1993 April (Box 14, Folder 112)
    A project of the Ford Foundation